Guide to the Plans and Profiles of Oregon Rivers 1923-1971
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
Plans and Profiles of Oregon Rivers
1923-1971
1926-1959
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center Special Collections & Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu
MAPS RiverPlans
Geological Survey (U.S.)
1.25 cubic feet, including 215 maps 1 oversize box
The Plans and Profiles of Oregon Rivers consist of detailed maps and profiles of rivers and streams, dam sites, and reservoirs, primarily in Oregon. The collection also includes some rivers in the bordering states of Washington, Idaho, and California.
The Plans and Profiles of Oregon Rivers consist of maps prepared by the U.S. Geological Survey documenting surveys of rivers and streams. The bulk of the collection (181 sheets) is comprised of river plans and profiles; the remainder of the collection (34 sheets) is dam site and reservoir plans. The plans depict topography adjacent to the river or stream, typically to an elevation high enough above the water surface to include the area of proposed reservoir sites, possible canals or conduits, or other structures related to water utilization. The profiles depict the elevation of the stream surface over a given reach of the waterway. The maps include general location maps and depict notable features such as roads, railroads, and landmarks. Some of the dam site and reservoir plans include topographic cross sections of the stream or river at the dam site. Information about the area and capacity of the reservoir are also included on many of these sheets.
The collection documents primarily rivers in Oregon; however, rivers and streams in bordering regions of Washington, Idaho, and California that are part of the Columbia, Snake, or Klamath drainages are also part of the collection. Maps of the major tributaries of the Willamette River, including the North and South Santiam and McKenzie Rivers are included. Many coastal rivers, such as the Nehalem, Nestucca, Siletz, Siuslaw, Trask, Umpqua, and Wilson Rivers are also depicted in the collection.
The plans range in scale from 1:2,400 to 1:31,680; most are at a scale of 1:4,800. Contour intervals are 10 or 20 feet on land and 1 to 15 feet on water.
Collection is open for research.
The Plans and Profiles of Oregon Rivers are arranged in two series: I. River Plans and Profiles, 1923-1969 and II. Dam Site and Reservoir Plans, 1937-1971. The maps are arranged alphabetically within each series.
These maps were transferred from the Oregon State University Libraries' map collection to the Special Collections & Archives Research Center in 2014.
The Planimetric Maps of Oregon and Washington (MAPS Planimetric) include detailed maps of the Columbia and Willamette Rivers and nearby towns and landscape features. The Historic Oregon Nautical Charts (MAPS Nautical) include superseded maps for navigable rivers and bays on the Oregon Coast. The Pacific Northwest Stream Survey Collection (MSS PNWStream) documents an extensive survey of the Columbia River and its tributaries conducted by the U.S. Fisheries and Wildlife Service in the 1930s-1940s.
Dams--Oregon--Maps.; Reservoirs--Oregon--Maps.; Rivers--Oregon--Maps.
Chetco River (Or.)--Maps.; Columbia River--Maps.; Coos River (Or.)--Maps.; Coquille River (Or.)--Maps.; Crooked River (Or.)--Maps.; Grande Ronde River (Or. and Wash.)--Maps.; Hood River (Or.: River)--Maps.; Klamath River (Or. and Calif.)--Maps.; McKenzie River (Or.)--Maps.; Nehalem River (Or.)--Maps.; Nestucca River (Or.)--Maps.; Rogue River (Klamath County-Curry County, Or.)--Maps.; Sandy River (Or.)--Maps.; Santiam River (Or.)--Maps.; Siletz River (Or.)--Maps.; Siuslaw River (Or.)--Maps.; Sixes River (Or.)--Maps.; Smith River (Douglas County, Or.)--Maps.; Snake River (Wyo.-Wash.)--Maps.; Trask River (Or.)--Maps.; Umatilla River (Or.)--Maps.; Umpqua River (Or.)--Maps.; Walla Walla River (Or. and Wash.)--Maps.; Wallowa River (Or.)--Maps.; Willamette River (Or.)--Maps.; Wilson River (Or.)--Maps.
Maps.; Topographic maps.
Water and Water Rights; Oregon; California; Washington (State); Idaho; Maps
- River Plans and Profiles, 1923-1969; Series I; 181 sheets
  Series I consists of plans depicting topography near rivers and profiles showing the change in elevation with distance over a given reach of the waterway.
  - Applegate River, 1950; 4 sheets (Box 1)
    In California and Oregon.
  - Chewaucan River, 1938; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - Columbia River, 1948; 11 sheets (Box 1)
    In Washington.
  - Cow Creek, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Crooked River, 1926; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - Deep Creek and Camas Creek, 1939; 4 sheets (Box 1)
  - Donner und Blitzen River, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Evans Creek, 1938; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - Grande Ronde River, 1934; 7 sheets (Box 1)
    In Washington and Oregon.
  - Hood River, 1939; 4 sheets (Box 1)
  - Jumpoff Joe Creek, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Kalama River, 1960; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - Klamath River, 1926-1957; 34 sheets (Box 1)
  - Little Butte Creek, 1938; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - Luckiamute River, 1938 (Box 1)
  - McKenzie River, 1926; 6 sheets (Box 1)
  - Middle Fork of Willamette River, 1927; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - Nehalem River, 1938; 7 sheets (Box 1)
  - Nestucca River, 1955-1969; 4 sheets (Box 1)
  - North Santiam River, 1944; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - Rogue River, 1955; 14 sheets (Box 1)
  - Sandy River, 1927; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - Separation Creek, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Siletz River, 1926; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - Silvies River, 1959-1962; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - Snake River, 1923-1932; 22 sheets (Box 1)
    In Oregon, Idaho, and Wyoming.
  - South Fork of Coos River, 1955; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - South Fork of Coquille River, 1926; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - South Santiam River, 1938; 5 sheets (Box 1)
  - South Umpqua River, 1938; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - South Yamhill River, 1938; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - Trask River, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Umpqua River, 1926; 9 sheets (Box 1)
  - Walla Walla River, 1932; 4 sheets (Box 1)
  - White River, 1933; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - Wilson River, 1955; 3 sheets (Box 1)
- Dam Site and Reservoir Plans, 1937-1971; Series II; 34 sheets
  Series II consists of maps of dam sites and reservoirs; some sheets include topographic cross sections of the stream or river at the dam site. The area (in acres) of the reservoir and capacity in acre-feet are provided in tabular and or graphic form on many sheets.
  - Blanca Lake and Troublesome Creek, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Bradley Creek, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Catherine Creek, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Coweman River, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Coverdale Reservoir, 1960 (Box 1)
    On Imnaha River.
  - Fishhawk Creek, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Gales Creek, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Grave Creek, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Green River, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Indian Creek, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Kiger Creek, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Lookout Point, 1937; 3 sheets (Box 1)
    On Middle Fork Willamette River.
  - Miscellaneous Dam Sites on Coastal Streams, 1957-1959; 2 sheets (Box 1)
    Include sites on the Nehalem, Alsea, and Siuslaw Rivers; Lake Creek; and the Chetco, Sixes, Pistol, and Millicoma Rivers on the south coast.
  - Mosby Creek, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Paterson Ridge, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Rondowa, 1948; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - Siletz River and West Olalla Creek, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Siuslaw River, 1964; 2 sheets (Box 1)
  - Smith River, 1958-1960; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - Squaw Creek, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Trask and McKenzie Rivers, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Umatilla River, 1938; 3 sheets (Box 1)
  - Walker Creek and Wiley Creek, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Wallowa and Lostine Rivers, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Willamina Creek, 1937 (Box 1)